Guide to the Bartos Company Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
The Bartos Company records
1928-1959
MS 2074
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
42.42
(19 containers)
The Bartos Company records includes include photographs, publicity materials, press clippings, magazine articles, and drawings documenting the furniture and woodworking business The Bartos Company (originally M. Bartos & Company). The bulk of the collection documents work produced by The Bartos Company from the 1920s to 1950s.
Bartos Company
Bartos, Harold
Bartos, Mor
Scope and Contents
The records include photographs, publicity materials, press clippings, magazine articles, and drawings documenting the furniture and woodworking business The Bartos Company (originally M. Bartos & Company). The bulk of the collection documents work produced by The Bartos Company from the 1920s to 1950s.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in five series: I. Period Drawings, 1926-1944. II. Photographs, 1930-1950. III. Publications and Publicity, 1924-1970. IV. Scrapbooks, 1938-1950. V. Samples, Ordering, and Administrative Materials, 1936-1940.
Records were arranged by the donor, Jim Bartos, but did not come to him in an original order from the company. Jim Bartos arranged records by type and subject, and staff of Manuscripts and Archives maintained most of that ordering, with the exception of the Scrabooks (reorganized into Series IV) and the Samples, Ordering, and Administrative Materials (reorganized into Series V).
Biographical / Historical
The Bartos Company was founded around 1900 by Mor Bartos, a Hungarian emigrant residing in New York City. Originally named M Bartos & Co., the company made high quality, custom-made period furniture for clients such as French & Co., Tiffany & Co., and William Randolph Hearst. In the early to mid-1900s companies such as French & Co. handled the interior decoration of furniture for rooms brought over from European houses to be reassembled in the United States. M Bartos & Co. made reproductions of original European furniture, intended to be indistinguishable from the originals. French & Co. used these furniture pieces to complete the reassembled rooms. M Bartos & Co. continued to work in this fashion until 1929.
Harold Bartos, son of Mor Bartos, took over the company in 1928 when Mor Bartos suddenly passed away from a heart attack. The company was then renamed The Bartos Company. After taking design and architectural classes at Columbia University, Harold Bartos became a designer and maker of furniture. He shifted the company from period to modern funiture and architectural woodwork. The Bartos Company made custom pieces to an architect's specifications as part of a larger project, such as executive offices, private residences, and public spaces. Examples of public projects include an acoustical ceiling for Alice Tully Hall at Lincoln Center and the redevelopment of the Great Hall at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In the 1940s, Harold Bartos co-founded and was the design producer of the Lehigh Furniture Co., which produced high quality furniture that could be ordered from a catalog. The Lehigh Furniture Co. was known for its innovative techniques with foam upholstery. The Lehigh Furniture Co. was later purchased by Litton Industries and merged with the Leopold Company to form Lehigh-Leopold Furniture. Throughout his career, Harold Bartos was active in The Architectural League of New York.
The Bartos Company dissolved in 1975 after the death of Harold Bartos.
Biographical information provided by Jim Bartos.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is available for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jim Bartos, 2017.
Separated Materials
Duplicate materials were removed from the collection. Acetate Negatives will be digitally reformatted and then destroyed.
Architecture, Domestic -- New York -- 20th Century; Furniture industry and trade -- United States -- 20th Century; Furniture design; Woodwork; Architectural Woodwork; Bartos Company
- Period Drawings, 1926–1944; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Most of the sketches and original drawings in this series are from French & Co. projects for which The Bartos Company supplied period furniture. Some drawings contain the product numbers for furniture pieces provided. Also found in this series are sketches and blueprints from the original IBM Building (1938-1977) located at 590 Madison Avenue in New York.
  Arrangement
  The drawings are arranged according to size.
  - French & Co. furniture
    - Custom-made furniture sketches, Circa 1920s (Box 1)
    - Custom-made furniture sketches, Circa 1920s (Box 2)
    - Custom-made furniture sketches, Circa 1920s (Box 3)
    - Custom-made furniture sketches, Circa 1920s (Box 4)
    - Custom-made furniture sketches, Circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Georgian rooms, product nos. 9737-12013, 1929 (Box 6)
    - Georgian rooms, product nos. 9737-12013, 1929 (Box 7)
    - Georgian paneling, doors, and trim, product no. 13245, Circa 1920s (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - White and gold room #6, product nos. 13976-13977, Circa 1920s (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Mr. Prentiss's bedroom, product nos. 7058-7059, Circa 1920s (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Georgian woodwork: McLean apt. - Mrs. Arthur Cohen, product nos. 10914-11391, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Louis XVI boudoir, product nos. 9312-13173, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Georgian room - plans 950 5th Ave, product nos. 6777-6779, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Georgian room, Circa 1920s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Georgian room; Mrs. Gottesman's living room, product nos. 16030, Circa 1920s (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - I.B.M. Building: Mr. Watson's ante rooms; Mr. Fortsen's bloq super, 1944 (Box 8)
- Photographs, 1930–1950; Series II
  The photographs in this series show the range of furniture pieces produced by The Bartos Company. The French & Co. and period photographs contain product numbers and dimensions on the back of the physical photograph. The furniture pieces in these photographs are the same furniture pieces depicted in the period drawings in Series I.
  This series is arranged by format type. Folders withing format types are arranged alphabetically.
  - Albums
    - Essential Wood Jig Company, Circa 1930s (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Large prints
    - Cyanamid Corporation of America, Circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - French & Co. furniture, Circa 1920s (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - French & Co. furniture, desks - sideboards, Circa 1920s (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - French & Co. furniture, Italian chair - tripod, product nos. 12829 - 12366, Circa 1920s (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - French & Co. furniture, oak console - Italian table, product nos. 34211 - 15606, Circa 1920s (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - French & Co., pine room, miscellaneous carving, Circa 1920s (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - French & Co., tables and desks, Circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Harold Bartos apartment, Circa 1940 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Lehigh Furniture, product nos. 2007-1950S, Circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Modern furniture, Circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Negatives
    - Furniture, product nos. 17704-17798, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Furniture, product nos. 16522 - 16657, Circa 1920s (Box 13a, Folder 1)
      Due to degredation, the physical negatives will be discarded after digitization.
  - Period photographs
    - Ark for A.S. Verway, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Bench, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
    - Chairs, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 7-10)
    - Desk, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 11-21)
    - Folding chair, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - French furniture, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Table, Circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 24-28)
  - Modern furniture
    - Alfreda, Circa 1940s (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Antoine photos, Circa 1940s (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - "Colliers House of Ideas," prints, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 31-33)
    - Exhibit - 15th Exhibition of Contemporary American Industrial Art, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - Johnson, no. 8494, Circa 1940s (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - Lehigh Furniture, circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - Neiman-Marcus, Circa 1940s (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Office furniture, Circa 1940s (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Tables and chairs, Circa 1930s-1950s (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Tables, chairs, and desks, Circa 1930s-1950s (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Publications and Publicity, 1924–1970; Series III
  This series contains trade catalogs, furniture and interior design publications, and publicity articles highlighting The Bartos Company. This series also includes a transcription of the CBS radio interview "The Cabinet Maker," which recorded Harold Bartos at his furniture shop.
  This series is arranged by format type. Folders within format types are arranged alphabetically.
  - Catalogs
    - Lehigh Furniture Corporation, 1954–1957 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - P.E. Geurin, cut sheets, Circa 1930s (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Robsjohn-Gibbings, Circa 1940s (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Trade, 1924–1970 (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Programs for events, 1924–1954 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Publications
    - American Designers Institute, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Americans at Work, "The Cabinet Maker", 1940 January 16 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Colliers, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "Colliers House of Ideas," publicity material, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Furniture Forum, 1949–1953 (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
    - Furniture Record, 1939 October 1 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - House & Garden, 1963 November (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - House Beautiful, 1940–1965 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Interiors, 1943 March (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Pencil Points, 1940–1942 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Publicity articles, 1938-1952, Undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Scrapbooks, 1938–1950; Series IV
  The scrapbooks in this series contain articles, clippings, and photographs documenting the work of The Bartos Company and Lehigh Furniture Company. The scrapbooks provide some of the only documentation of Harold Bartos's work with the Lehigh Furniture Company.
  - Articles and clippings, 1948–1950 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Articles, clippings, and photographs, 1938–1946 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, circa 1940 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Samples, Ordering, and Administrative Materials, 1936–1940; Series V
  This series contains administrative materials of The Bartos Company. Included are wooden marquetry inlay samples and an Order and Receipt Book. The photo catalog books contain photographs of each piece of furniture produced that was available to order. Most photographs have the product number and dimensions written on the back of the photograph.
  - Administrative materials
    - Letter from David Miller to Charles Hanson, 1939 April 19 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      The letter is from David Miller, Secretary of the Manufacturing Woodworkers Association to Charles W. Hanson, President of the Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Harold Bartos served on the Executive Committee of the Manufacturing Woodworkers Association.
    - Partial list of completed contracts, Circa 1940s (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Order and receipt book, 1936–1940 (Box 18, Folder 3-8)
  - Marquetry inlay samples, Circa 1930s (Box 19)
  - Photo catalog books
    - Key Book #1, product nos. 15392 - 13001, Circa 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
    - Key Book #2, product nos. 6565 - 16910, Circa 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Key Book #2, product nos. 6565 - 16910, Circa 1920s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
    - Key Book #3, product nos. 7100 - 6541A, Circa 1920s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 4-6)
    - Key Book #4, product nos. 8636 - 7110, Circa 1920s-1940s (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - Miscellaneous Book #1, period furniture, product nos. 15372 - 13731, Circa 1940s (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
    - Miscellaneous Book #2, modern furniture, product nos. 1979 - 13001, Circa 1940s (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Book #2, modern furniture, product nos. 1979 - 13001, Circa 1940s (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - Robsjohn-Gibbings #1, product nos. 6781C - 15089, Circa 1930s (Box 23, Folder 3-5)
    - Robsjohn-Gibbings #1, product nos. 6781C - 15089, Circa 1930s (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
    - Weber Furniture, product nos. 17603 - 16518, Circa 1940s (Box 24, Folder 3-5)